

GALADRIEL
1 "I amar prestar sen: han mathon ne nen, han mathon ne chae...a han noston ned wilith."  The world is changed: I feel it in the water, I feel it in the earth, I smell it in the air...Much that once was is lost, for none now live who remember it.
2 It began with the forging of the Great Rings.
3 Three were given to the Elves, immortal, wisest...fairest of all beings.
4 Seven to the Dwarf Lords, great miners and craftsmen of the mountain halls.
5 And Nine...nine rings were gifted to the race of Men who, above all else, desire power. For within these rings was bound the strength and will to govern each race.
6 But they were all of them deceived.
7 ...for another ring was made.
8 In the land of Mordor, in the fires of Mount Doom, the Dark Lord Sauron forged in secret a Master Ring to control all others.
9 ...and into this Ring he poured his cruelty, his malice and his will to dominate all life.
10 One Ring to rule them all...
11 One by one the Free lands of Middle earth fell to the power of the ring.
12 But there were some...who resisted.
13 A last alliance of Men and Elves marched against the armies of Mordor.
14 On the slopes of Mount Doom they fought for the freedom of Middle- Earth.
15 Victory was near!
16 But the power of the Ring could not be undone.
17 It was in this moment..when all hope had faded, that Isildur, son of the king, took up his father's sword.
18 Sauron, the enemy of the Free Peoples of Middle Earth, was defeated.
19 The Ring passed to Isildur...who had this one chance to destroy evil forever.
20 But the hearts of Men are easily corrupted. And the Ring of Power has a will of its own.
21 It betrayed Isildur to his death.
22 And some things that should not have been forgotten...were lost.
23 History became legend...legend became myth.
24 And for two and a half thousand years the Ring passed out of all knowledge.
25 Until, when chance came, it ensnared a new bearer!
26 The Ring came to the creature Gollum, who took it deep into the tunnels of the Misty Mountains.
27 And there, it consumed him. A RASPY VOICE mutters in the half light...
28 The Ring brought to Gollum unnatural long life. For five hundred years it poisoned his mind. And in the gloom of Gollum's cave...
29 It waited.
30 Darkness crept back into the forests of the world. Rumor grew of a Shadow in the East...whispers of a nameless fear. And the Ring of Power perceived...its time had now come. It abandoned Gollum.
31 But something happened then the Ring did not intend...
32 It was picked up by the most unlikely creature imaginable...
33 A Hobbit....Bilbo Baggins of the Shire.
34 For the time will soon come when Hobbits will shape the fortunes of all.
35 Frodo...
36 ...your coming to us is as the footsteps of doom. You bring great evil here, Ringbearer.
37 ...he has fallen into shadow.
38 The Quest stands upon the edge of a knife. Stray but a little and it will fail, to the ruin of all...Yet hope remains while the company is true.
39 Do not let your hearts be troubled. Go now and rest for you are weary with sorrow and much toil.
40 Tonight you will sleep in peace.
41 ...one who has seen the eye.
42 Will you look into the mirror?
43 Even the wisest cannot tell for the mirror shows many things...things that were ..things that are...and some things that have not yet come to pass.
44 I know what it is you saw...for it is also in my mind. It is the future, Frodo. It is what will come to pass if you should fail.
45 The fellowship is breaking. It has already begun. He will try to take the ring. You know of whom I speak. One by one, it will destroy them all.
46 You offer it to me freely...I do not deny that my heart has greatly desired this.
47 In place of the Dark Lord, you would have a Queen, not dark, but beautiful and terrible as the Dawn. Treacherous as the Sea! Stronger than the foundations of the earth...all shall love me and despair!
48 I pass the test.  I will diminish and go into the west and remain Galadriel.
49 You are the ring-bearer, Frodo...to bear a ring of power is to be alone. This task was appointed to you, and if you do not find a way, no one will.
50 Even the smallest person can change the course of the future.
51 Farewell, Frodo Baggins. I give you the light of Earendil, our most beloved star.
52 May it be a light for you in dark places, when all other lights go out.


ELROND
1 Welcome to Rivendell, Frodo Baggins.
2 You have found your way to the last homely house east of the sea. The elves of Imladris have dwelt within this valley for three thousand years through few of my kin now remain.
3 His strength returns.
4 And yet to have come so far still bearing the Ring...the hobbit has shown extraordinary resilience to its evil.
5 Gandalf, the enemy is moving. Sauron's forces are massing in the east. His eye is fixed on Rivendell. And Saruman, you tell me, has betrayed us. Our list of allies grows thin.
6 This evil cannot be concealed by the power of the Elves...We do not have the strength to fight both Mordor and Isengard...Gandalf...the ring cannot stay here.
7 This peril belongs to all Middle earth. They must decide how to end it. Not just for themselves but for those who come after.
8 The time of the Elves is over. My people are leaving these shores. Who will you look to when we have gone? The dwarves? They hide in their mountains seeking riches. They care nothing for the troubles of others.
9 Men? Men are weak. The race of Men is failing. The blood of Numenor is all but spent, its pride and dignity forgotten. It is because of men the Ring survives.
10 I was there, Gandalf...I was there three thousand years ago when Isildur took the ring.
11 I was there the day the strength of Men failed.
12 Isildur...hurry...follow me!
13 I let Isildur into the heart of Mount Doom, where the ring was forged: the one place it could be destroyed.
14 Cast it into the fire...destroy it!
15 Isildur!!
16 It should have ended that day, but evil was allowed to endure. Isildur kept the Ring...and the line of Kings was broken. There's no strength left in the world of Men. They're scattered, divided, leaderless.
17 He turned from that path a long time ago. He has chosen exile.
18 Strangers from distant lands ... friends of old. You have been summoned here to answer the threat of Mordor. Middle-earth stands upon the brink of destruction. None can escape it. You will unite...or you will fall. Each race is bound to this fate...this one doom...
19 Bring forth the ring, Frodo.
20 You have only one choice..the ring must be destroyed.
21 The ring cannot be destroyed, Gimli, son of Gloin, by any craft that we here possess. The ring was made in the fires of Mount Doom...only there can it be unmade. It must be taken deep into Mordor, and cast back into the fiery chasm from whence it came. One of you must do this.
22 No, Indeed...it is hardly possible to separate you...even when he is summoned to a secret council and you are not.
23 Nine companions ... so be it.  You shall be the "Fellowship of the ring"


BILBO
1 What's this?
2 A Ring.
3 No, thank you! We don't want any more visitors, well wishers, or distant relations.
4 Gandalf?
5 My dear Gandalf!
6 Come on, come in! Welcome, welcome!!
7 Tea? Or maybe something stronger... I've a few bottles of the Old Winyard left, 1296...a very good year, almost as old as I am. It was laid down by my father. What say we open one, eh?
8 I was expecting you some time last week. Not that it matters, you come and go as you please, always have done, always will. You've caught me a bit unprepared, I'm afraid...we've only got cold chicken, bit of pickle, some cheese here...ooh, no, that might be a little risky...
9 Er, we've got raspberry jam and apple tart...got some custard somewhere. Not much for Afters, I'm afraid. Oh no...we're alright...I've just found some sponge cake. Nice little snack. Hope it's enough.  I could do you some eggs if you like?
10 Oh..right. You don't mind if...?
11 I'm not home.
12 I've got to get away from these confounded relatives, hanging on the bell all day, never giving me a moment's peace. I want to see mountains again...mountains, Gandalf... and then find somewhere quiet where I can finish my book...Oh, Tea!
13 Yes, yes...it's all inhand. All the arrangements are made.
14 'Course he does, he's a Baggins...not some block headed Bracegirdle from Hardbottle!
15 Yes, yes.
16 I know. He'd probably come with me if I asked him. I think, in his heart, Frodo's still in love with the Shire, the woods and the fields... little rivers.
17 I am old, Gandalf... Bilbo looks at Gandalf sadly...
18 I know I don't look it, but I'm beginning to feel it in my heart.
19 I feel thin...sort of stretched, like butter scraped over too much bread. I need a holiday...a very long holiday and I don't expect I shall return...in fact, I mean not to.
20 Old Toby, the finest weed in Southfarthing!
21 Ohhhh,  Gandalf my old friend...this will be a night to remember!
22 So, there I was...at the mercy of three monstrous trolls...Have you ever heard of a troll? Do you know what a Troll is? Great big nasty twenty foot high smelly things..and they're arguing...arguing about how they were going to cook us!
23 Whether it be turned on a spit or minced in a pie or whether they were going to sit on us one by one and squash us into jelly! But they spent so long arguing the whether-to's and why-for's that the sun's first light crept over the top of the trees...and turned them all to stone!
24 Dragon? Nonsense...hasn1t been a dragon in these parts for a thousand years!
25 My dear Bagginses, and Boffins, tooks and Brandybucks...Grubbs, Chubbs, Hornblowers, Bolgers, Bracegirdles and Proudfoots...
26 Today is my one hundred and eleventh birthday. Yes, and alas...Eleventy- one years is far too short a time to live among such excellent and admirable Hobbits! Tremendous outburst of approval!
27 I don't know half of you half as well as I should like; and I like less than half of you as well as well as you deserve.
28 I have..things to do and I have put this off for far too long...
29 I regret to announce, this is the end. I am going now. I bid you all a very fond farewell!!
30 Goodbye.
31 Come on, Gandalf! Did you see their faces?
32 It was just a bit of fun. Oh, you're probably right as usual.
33 I'm leaving everything to him.
34 Yes, yes, it's in an envelope...over there on the mantelpiece. Gandalf frowns at the empty mantelpiece...Bilbo suddenly feels his waistcoat with a look of guilty surprise.
35 No, wait. It's here in my pocket. Isn't that...isn't' that odd now? Yet, after all, why not? Why shouldn't I keep it?
36 Well, no...and yes. Now it comes to it, I don't feel like parting with it. It's mine. I found it. It came to me!
37 Well, if I'm angry, it's your fault! It's mine. My own, my precious.
38 So? What business is it of yours what I do with my own things?
39 You want it for yourself!
40 You're right, Gandalf...the ring must go to Frodo.
41 It's late, the road is long... yes, it is time.
42 Hmmm?
43 Oh, yes.
44 I've thought up and ending for my book..."And he lived happily ever after to the end of his days."
45 Goodbye, Gandalf.
46 It's mine, my own, my precious.
47 ... it's a dangerous business, Frodo, going out your door...you step onto the road, and if you don't keep your feet, there's not knowing where you might be swept off to.
48 Hello, Frodo, my lad!
49 I meant to go back...wander the paths of Mirkwood, visit Laketown, see the Lonely Mountain again...but age, it seems, has finally caught up with me.
50 My dear boy...
51 My old sword "Sting"...here, take it!
52 Yes, yes, made by the Elves, you know. The blade glows blue when Orcs are close...and it's times like that, my lad, when you have to be extra careful.
53 Here's a pretty thing. Mithril, as light as a feather, and as hard as dragon scales. Let me see you put it on. Come on.
54 Oh! My old Ring...
55 I should very much like to hold it again, one last time. Bilbo reaches forward, eyes locked on the ring.
56 Oh!
57 I'm sorry, that I brought this upon you, my boy...I'm sorry that you must carry this burden. I'm sorry for everything.


FRODO
1 You're late.
2 It's wonderful to see you, Gandalf!
3 What news of the outside world? Tell me everything!
4 You know Bilbo...he's got he whole place in an uproar.
5 Half the Shire's been invited...
6 He's up to something.
7 Alright then..keep your secrets. Before you came along we Bagginses were very well thought of.
8 Never had any adventures or did anything unexpected.
9 Whatever you did...you've been officially labelled as a Disturber of the Peace.
10 Gandalf... I'm glad you're back.
11 Go on, Sam, ask Rosie for a dance.
12 Oh, no you don't. Go on.
13 Bilbo! Watch out for the dragon!!
14 Speech!
15 Bilbo! Bilbo!
16 He's gone, hasn't he? Frodo steps into the living room.
17 He talked for so long about leaving...I didn't think he'd really do it.
18 Gandalf?
19 Where are you going?
20 What things?
21 You've only just arrived! I don't understand...
22 What are you doing?
23 Nothing...there's nothing. Wait...
24 It's some form of Elvish...I can't read it.
25 Mordor?
26 Bilbo found it...in Gollom's cave.
27 But he was destroyed...Sauron was destroyed.
28 Alright!
29 We put it away, we keep it hidden! We never speak of it again. No one know it's here, do they?
30 Do they, Gandalf?
31 Shire! Baggins! That will lead them here!
32 Take it! Take it!
33 You must take it.
34 I'm giving it to you!
35 But it cannot stay in the Shire!
36 What must I do?
37 Where? Where shall I go?
38 Bree? What about you?
39 And the ring will be safe there?
40 I can cut across country easily enough.
41 This is what?
42 Come on, Sam.
43 Remember what Bilbo used to say...it's a dangerous business...
44 What are you talking about?
45 What did he say?
46 Sam...we're still in the Shire...what could possibly happen?
47 I think we should get off the road.
48 Get off the road!
49 Nothing.
50 I have to leave the Shire...Sam and I must get to Bree.
51 How far to the nearest crossing?
52 Come on.
53 We're headed for the prancing pony.
54 We wish to stay at the inn...our business is our own.
55 Excuse me.
56 Underhill...my name's Underbill.
57 We're friends of Gandalf the Grey...can you tell him we've arrived?
58 Sam, he'll be here. He'll come.
59 Excuse me, that man in the corner, who is he?
60 Strider.
61 Pippin!
62 What do you want?
63 I carry nothing.
64 Who are you?
65 Yes.
66 Where are they?
67 Where are you taking us?
68 We have no choice but to trust him.
69 What are you doing?
70 Put it out, you fools! Put it out! Frodo desperately kicks dirt on the fire!
71 Go! !
72 Gandalf... Gandalf?
73 Where am I?
74 Gandalf!
75 What happened, Gandalf? Why didn't you meet us?
76 Gandalf! What is it? Gandalf returns his attention to Frodo.
77 Bilbo!
78 Bilbo!
79 "There and back again: A Hobbit's tale" by Bilbo Baggins.
80 This is wonderful.
81 I miss the Shire...I spent all my childhood pretending I was off somewhere else...off with you, on one of your adventures...  But my own adventure, turned out to be quite different...I'm not like you, Bilbo.
82 Packed already?
83 I thought you wanted to see the Elves, Sam?
84 More than anything.
85 You're right, Sam. Frodo looks at Sam...
86 ...we did what we set out to do. Frodo opens his hand, the Ring sits in his Palm.
87 The ring will be safe in Rivendell. I am ready to go home.
88 I will take it...I will take it...I will take the Ring to Mordor.
89 Though...I do not know the way.
90 It's so light!
91 We will go through the mines.
92 It's a riddle...
93 Speak, friend, and enter. What's the Elvish for friend?
94 There's something down there.
95 Gollum!
96 He escaped the dungeons of Barad- dur?
97 It's a pity Bilbo didn't kill him when he had the chance.
98 I wish the ring had never come to me...I wish none of this had happened.
99 Aragorn! Aragorn!
100 I'm alright. I'm not hurt.
101 Gandalf!
102 Gandalf!
103 No!
104 What will I see?
105 Gandalf!
106 If you ask it of me, I will give you the One Ring.
107 I cannot do this alone...
108 Then I know what I must do. It's just...I'm afraid to do it.
109 I know what you would say, and it would seem like wisdom but for the warning of my heart.
110 There is no other way.
111 No...
112 You are not yourself.
113 It has taken Boromir.
114 Stay away!
115 Can you protect me from yourself?
116 Would you destroy it?
117 I know...Look after the others, especially Sam...he will not understand.
118 I wish the ring had never come to me..I wish none of this had happened...
119 No, Sam.
120 Go back, Sam. I'm going to Mordor alone.
121 You can't swim.
122 Sam!
123 Oh, Sam!
124 Come on then..
125 Mordor! I hope the others find a safer road.
126 I don't suppose we'll ever see them again.
127 Sam?
128 I'm glad you're with me.


GANDALF
1 A Wizard is never late, Frodo Baggins, nor is he early. He arrives precisely when he means to.
2 You didn't think I'd miss your Uncle Bilbo's birthday?
3 What, everything? Far too eager and curious for a Hobbit. Most unnatural...
4 Well, what can I tell you? Life in the wide world goes on much as if it has past age. Full of its own comings and goings, scarcely even aware of the existence of Hobbits...
5 ...for which I am very thankful.
6 Ah, the long expected party. So, how is the old rascal? I hear it's going to be a Party of Special Magnificence.
7 Oh, well...that should please him.
8 Good gracious, me.
9 Oh, really?
10 Indeed?
11 If you're referring to the incident with the Dragon...I was barely involved...all I did was give your Uncle a little nudge out the door.
12 Oh, really?
13 So am I, dear boy...so am I
14 And what about very old friends?
15 Bilbo Baggins!
16 It's good to see you. One hundred and eleven years old, who would believe it!
17 You haven't aged a day! Gandalf and Bilbo laugh together and enter Bag End.
18 Just tea, thank you.
19 No, not at all. Go ahead. A sudden loud knock on the front door.
20 So, you mean to go through with your plan, then?
21 Frodo suspects something.
22 You will tell him, won't you?
23 He's very fond of you.
24 Meridoc Brandybuck and Peregrin Took...I might have known!
25 I suppose you think that was terribly clever?
26 There are many magic rings in the world, Bilbo Baggins, and none of them should be used lightly.
27 You will keep an eye on Frodo, won't you?
28 What about this ring of yours? Is that staying too?
29 I think you should leave the Ring behind, Bilbo. Is that so hard?
30 There's no need to get angry.
31 Precious? It's been called that before, but not by you.
32 I think you've had that ring quite long enough.
33 Bilbo Baggins do not take me for some conjurer of cheap tricks!
34 I am not trying to rob you. I am trying to help you.
35 All you long years we've been friends...trust me as you once did. Let it go!
36 Bilbo?
37 The ring is still in your pocket.
38 I'm sure you will, my dear friend.
39 Goodbye Bilbo.
40 Until our next meeting.
41 Riddles in the dark.
42 My precious...precious..
43 ...my own.
44 Bilbo's ring.
45 He's gone to stay with the Elves. He's left you Bag End...
46 ...along with all his possessions.
47 The ring is yours now. But it somewhere out of sight.
48 I have some things I must see to.
49 Questions. Questions that need answering.
50 Neither do I. Keep it secret, keep it safe.
51 The year 3434 of the Second Age...here follows the account of Isildur, High King of Gondor, and the finding of the ring of power.
52 It has come to me...the ring of power! It shall be an heirloom of my Kingdom...all those who follow in my bloodline shall be bound to its fate, for I will risk no hurt to the ring... it is precious to me, though I buy it with great pain...
53 The marking upon the band begin to fade...the writing which at first was as clear as red flame, has all but disappeared...a secret now that only fire can tell...
54 Is it secret? Is it safe?
55 Hold out your hand, Frodo...it is quite cool.
56 What can you see? Can you see anything?
57 ...these are markings.
58 There are few who can...the language is that of Mordor, which I will not utter here.
59 This is the one ring forged by the dark lord, Sauron, in the fires of Mt Doom...taken by Isildur from the hand of Sauron himself.
60 For sixty years the ring lay quiet in Bilbo's keeping, prolonging his life, delaying old age...but no longer, Frodo. Evil is stirring in Mordor. The ring has awoken. It has heard its master's call.
61 No, Frodo. The spirit of Sauron has endured. His life force is bound to the ring and the ring survived. Sauron has returned. His Orcs have multiplied...his fortress of Barad- dur is rebuilt in the land of Mordor. Sauron needs only this ring to cover all the lands in the second darkness. He is seeking it, seeking it, all his thought is bent on it. For the ring yearns, above all else, to return to the hand of its master: they are one, the ring and the dark lord. Frodo, he must never find out.
62 There is one other who knew that Bilbo had the Ring. I looked everywhere for the creature Gollum, but the enemy found him first.
63 I don't know how long they tortured him...but amidst the endless screams and inane babble, they discerned two words.
64 No, Frodo...
65 You cannot offer me this ring.
66 Don't tempt me, Frodo. I dare not take it, not even to keep it safe.
67 Understand, Frodo...I would use this Ring from a desire to do good...but through me, it would wield a power too great and terrible to imagine.
68 No, no it can't.
69 You must leave, and leave quickly. Get out of the Shire.
70 Make for the village of Bree.
71 I will, be waiting for you at the Inn of the Prancing Pony.
72 I don't know, Frodo. I don't have any answers. I must see the Head of my Order. He is both wise and powerful. Trust me, Frodo. He'll know what to go.
73 You'll have to leave the name of Baggins behind you...for that name is not safe outside the Shire.
74 Travel only by day and stay off the road.
75 My dear Frodo, Hobbits really are amazing creatures. You can learn all that there is to know about their ways in a month, and yet, after a hundred years, they can still surprise you.
76 Get down!
77 Confound it all! Samwise Gamgee, have you been eavesdropping?
78 It's a little late for trimming the hedges, don't you think?
79 What did you hear? Speak!
80 No?
81 Perhaps not. I've thought of a better use for you.
82 Come along, Samwise...keep up...
83 Be careful, both of you. The Enemy has many spies in his service, many ways of hearing...birds, beasts...
84 Is it safe?
85 Never put it on, for then the agents of the Dark Lord will be drawn to its power...Always remember, Frodo, the ring is trying to get back to its master...it wants to be found.
86 Saruman!
87 Beyond any doubt.
88 All these long years it was in the Shire, under my very nose.
89 We still have time...time enough to counter Sauron...if we act quickly.
90 The eye of Sauron.
91 You know this? How?
92 A palantir is a dangerous tool, Saruman.
93 They are not all accounted for, the lost seeing-stones...we do not know who else may be watching.
94 The nine!
95 They have reached the Shire? Saruman shrugs...
96 Tell me, friend, when did Saruman the wise abandon reason for madness?
97 You are in the House of Elrond, and it is ten o'clock in the morning on October the twenty-fourth, if you want to know.
98 Yes, I'm here and you're lucky to be here, too. A few more hours and you would have been beyond our aid. You have some strength in you, my dear Hobbit.
99 I'm sorry Frodo.
100 I was delayed.
101 There is only one Lord of the Ring. Only one who can bend it to his will...and he does not share power.
102 Nothing, Frodo...
103 Sam has hardly left your side.
104 By the skills of Lord Elrond, you're beginning to mend.
105 That wound will never fully heal. He will carry it the rest of his life.
106 It is a burden he should never have to had to bear. We can ask no more of Frodo.
107 His treachery runs deeper than you know. By foul craft, Saruman has crossed Orc with Goblin Men...he is breeding an army in the caverns of Isengard. An army that can move in Sunlight and cover great distance at speed. Saruman is coming for the Ring.
108 It is in Men that we must place our hope.
109 There is one who could unite them, one who could re claim the thrown of Gondor.
110 Aragorn is right...we cannot use it.
111 Do you not understand? While we bicker among ourselves, Sauron's power grows! No one will escape it. You will all be destroyed, your homes burnt and your families put to the sword!
112 I will help you bear this burden, Frodo Baggins, as long as it is yours to bear.
113 We must hold to his course west of the misty Mountains for forty days. If our luck holds, the Gap of Rohan will still be open to us. From there, our road turns east, to Mordor.
114 No, Gimli. I would not take the road through Moria unless I had no other choice.
115 Spies of Saruman. The passage South is being watched.
116 We must take the pass of Caradhras!
117 It's Saruman.
118 No!
119 Losto Caradhras, sedho, hodo, nuitho I ruith. Sleep Caradhras, be still, lie still, hold your wrath.
120 Let the ringbearer decide.
121 Frodo?
122 So be it.
123 Itidin...it mirrors only starlight and moonlight.
124 It reads, "The door of Durin, Lord of Moria. Speak, friend, and enter."
125 It's quite simple. If you are a friend, speak the password and the doors will open.
126 Annon edhellen, edro hi ammen!
127 Oh...mellon.
128 Into the mines!
129 We now have but one choice...we must face the long dark of Moria. Be on your guard...there are older and fouler things than the Orcs in the deep places of the world.
130 Quietly, now. It's a four day journey to the other side. Let us hope that our presence will go unnoticed.
131 I have no memory of this place.
132 It's Gollum.
133 He's been following us for three days.
134 Escaped...or was set loose. And now the Ring has drawn him here...he will never be rid of his need for it. He hates and loves the ring, as he hates and loves himself. Smeagol's life is a sad story.
135 Yes...Smeagol he was once called...Before the ring came to him, before it drove him mad.
136 Pity? It was pity that stayed Bilbo's hand. Many that live deserve death, and some that die deserve life. Can you give it to them, Frodo?
137 Do not be too eager to deal out death in judgment...even the very wise cannot see all ends. My heart tells me that Gollum has some part to play yet, for good or ill, before this is over. The pity of Bilbo may rule the fate of many.
138 So do all who live to see such times, but that is not for them to decide. All we have to decide is what to do with the time that is given to us.
139 There are other forces at work in this world, Frodo, besides the will of evil. Bilbo was meant to find the ring. In which case, you also were meant to have it...and that is an encouraging thought,  Ah! That it's that way!
140 No, but the air doesn't smell so foul down there. If in doubt, Meriadoc, always follow your nose!  Yes...
141 Let me risk a little more light.
142 Behold! The great realm and Dwarf city of Dwarrowdelf!
143 Gimli!!
144 "Here lies Balin, son of Fudin, Lord of Moria." He is dead, then. It's as I had feared.
145 "They have taken the Bridge and the second hall: we have barred the gates...but cannot hold them for long...the ground shakes...drums in the deep...we cannot get out. A shadow moves in the dark. Will no- one save us? They are coming."
146 Fool of a Took! Throw yourself in next time and rid us of your stupidity!
147 I think there's more to this hobbit than meets the eye.
148 To the bridge of Khazad-dum!
149 This way!
150 A Balrog..a demon of the ancient world! This foe is beyond any of you!  Run! Quickly!
151 Lead them on, Aragorn. The bridge is near.
152 Do as I say; swords are no more use here.
153 Over the bridge! Fly!
154 You cannot pass!
155 I am a servant of the Secret Fire, wielder of the flame of Anor. The dark fire will not avail you, flame of Udun.
156 Go back to the shadow!
157 You shall not pass!!
158 Fly, you fools!
159 So do all who lie to see such times...but that is not for them to decide. All we have to decide is what to do with the time that is given us.


SAM
1 I think I'll just have myself another ale.
2 I ain't been dropping no eaves, sir! Honest. I was just cutting the grass under the window there, if you follow me...
3 I heard raised voices...
4 Nothing important...that is, I heard a good deal about a ring...and a Dark Lord. And something about the end of the world, but...Please, Mr. Gandalf, sir, don't hurt me! Don't turn me into anything unnatural!
5 This is it.
6 If I take one more step it'll be the farthest away from home I've ever been.
7 Mr. Frodo. Mr. Frodo!
8 I thought I lost you.
9 It's just something Gandalf said...
10 He said..."Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."  And I don't mean to.
11 What's the meaning of this!
12 You've been into Farmer Maggot's crop!
13 Trust a Brandybuck and a Took.
14 A shortcut to what?
15 Frodo?
16 Anything?
17 Get down!
18 Frodo!
19 What do we do now?
20 You've had a whole half already.
21 That fellow's done nothing but stare at you since we've arrived.
22 Let him go or I'll have you, Longshanks!
23 Did you hear that, Bill? Rivendell! We're going to see the Elves!
24 We saved some for you, Mr. Frodo.
25 Back, you devils!
26 No!
27 Frodo!
28 Mr. Frodo!!
29 Help him, Strider!
30 Do something.
31 We are six days from Rivendell.
32 He'll never make it!
33 Athelas?
34 Kingsfoil. Aye. It's a weed.
35 She's an elf.
36 What are you doing! Those Wraiths are still out there!
37 Frodo! Frodo! Bless you, you're awake!!
38 We were worried about you--weren't we, Mr. Gandalf?
39 No, what have I forgotten? Pull back to reveal
40 No harm in being prepared.
41 I do...
42 I did. It's just...we did what Gandalf wanted, didn't we? We got the Ring this far, to Rivendell...and I thought... seeing as how you're on the mend, we'd be off soon. Off home.
43 Here!
44 Mr. Frodo's not gong anywhere without me.
45 Should not be too hard...
46 What is that?
47 Bye, Bill.
48 Goodbye, Bill.
49 Well, there's an eye opener and no mistake!
50 Mr. Frodo!
51 I think I'm getting the hang of this.
52 He's alive!
53 Mr. Frodo?
54 Mr. Frodo!
55 Mr. Frodo!
56 Not alone, Frodo. Mr. Frodo!
57 Of course you are...and I'm coming with you!
58 I made a promise, Mr. Frodo...a promise.  "Don't you leave him, Samwise Gamgee."  And I don't mean to...I don't mean to.
59 Strider'll look after them.
60 We may yet, Mr. Frodo. We may.


MERRY
1 No, no..the big one...the big one!
2 You're supposed to stick it in the ground!
3 Outside!
4 That was good!
5 Hello Frodo
6 Sam, hold this...
7 I don't know why he's so upset, it's only a couple of carrots.
8 Yes, Pippin, my point is, he's clearly over reacting.
9 Ow...I think I've broken something.
10 Oh.
11 What? That was just a detour...a shortcut.
12 What was that?
13 The Black rider was looking for something...or someone...Frodo?
14 Right...Buckleberry Ferry...follow me !
15 There's another one!! Frodo, this way! !
16 Frodo, follow me!
17 Get the ropes, Sam.
18 The brandwine bridge...twenty miles.
19 This, my friend, is a pint.
20 How do, we know this Strider is a friend of Gandalf?
21 I don't think he knows about second breakfast, Pip.
22 I wouldn't count on it.
23 Pippin!
24 Tomatoes, sausages, and crispy bacon.
25 They're close.
26 Frodo! Frodo!
27 Oi! We're coming too! You'll have to send us home tied up in a sack to stop us.
28 Well, that rules you out, Pip.
29 Quite good, Pippin.
30 What do you suppose that means?
31 No. I don't think we are. Shhhh, Gandalf's thinking.
32 What?
33 He's remembered!
34 What do they say about him?
35 Where's Frodo?
36 Frodo!
37 Hide here, quick!
38 He's leaving.
39 Pippin!
40 Aaaaagh! Boromir! Boromir!


PIPPIN
1 It is in the ground.
2 It was your idea.
3 Let's get another one!
4 Frodo! Merry, it's Frodo Baggins.
5 And some cabbages...and those three bags of potatoes that we lifted last week. And then the mushrooms the week before.
6 Run!
7 That was close.
8 Mushrooms!
9 What is going on?
10 What's that?
11 It comes in pints? I'm getting one!
12 Baggins? Sure, I know a Baggins...he's over there...
13 Frodo Baggins. He's my second cousin once removed, on his mother's side and my third cousin twice removed on his father's side...if you follow me.
14 Steady on, Frodo!
15 What about breakfast?
16 We've had one, yes...but what about Second Breakfast?
17 What about Elvenses, Luncheon, Afternoon Tea, dinner...he knows about them, doesn't he?
18 Oh, that's nice...ash on my tomatoes!
19 Is he going to die?
20 Who is she?
21 Where are you taking him?
22 What are they saying?
23 Anyway...you need people of intelligence on this sort of mission...quest...thing...
24 Great. Where are we going?
25 Thanks.
26 Are we lost?
27 Merry!
28 I'm hungry.
29 Come on...
30 What's he doing?
31 No!
32 Aaaaagh! Boromir! Boromir!


SARUMAN
1 Smoke rises once more from the mountain of doom...the shadow takes shape in the darkness of Mordor; the hour grows late...and Gandalf the Grey rides to Isengard seeking my counsel...
2 For that is why you have come, is it not, my old friend?
3 Are you sure of this?
4 So the ring of power has been found?
5 And yet you did not have the wit to see it! Your love of the Halfling's leaf has clearly slowed your mind.
6 Time? What time do you think we have?
7 Sauron has regained much of his former strength. He cannot yet take physical form...but his spirit has lost none of its potency. Concealed within his fortress, the lord of Mordor sees all. His gaze pierces cloud, shadow, earth, and flesh. You know of what I speak, Gandalf...a great Eye, lidless, wreathed in flame.
8 He is gathering all evil to him.
9 Very soon he will have summoned an army great enough to launch an assault upon Middle earth.
10 I have seen it.
11 Why? Why should we fear to use it?
12 The hour is later than you think. Sauron's forces are already moving...the Nine have left Minas Morgul.
13 They crossed the river Isen in Midsummer's eve, disguised as riders in black.
14 They will find the ring...and kill the one who carries it.
15 You did not seriously think a Hobbit could contend with the will of Sauron? There are none who can.
16 Against the power of Mordor, there can be no victory. We must join with him, Gandalf. We must join with Sauron. It would be wise, my friend.
17 I gave you the chance of aiding me willingly, but you have elected the way of pain.
18 The power of Isengard is at your command, Sauron, Lord of the Earth.
19 Build me an army worth of Mordor.
20 We have work to do.
21 Rip them all down.
22 This was once the great Watchtower of Amon Sul. We shall rest here tonight.
23 There are for you. Keep them close. I'm going to have a look around. Stay here.
24 Get up! So much for the power of the Ring or embrace your own destruction!
25 So you have chosen death!
26 So, Gandalf...you try to lead them over Caradhras. And if that fails...where then will you go?
27 If the mountain defeats you, will you risk a more dangerous road?
28 Moria. You fear to go into those mines, don't you? The dwarves delved too greedily and too deep.
29 You know what they awoke in, the darkness of Khazad-dum. Shadow and flame.
30 They were Elves once. Taken by the Dark Powers ... tortured and mutilated...a ruined and terrible form of life. And now...perfected. My fighting Uruk-Hai. Whom do you serve?
31 Hunt them down. Do not stop until they are found. You do not know pain. You do not know fear. You will taste man-flesh. Saruman turns to Lurtz.
32 One of the Halflings carries something of great value...bring him to me...alive and unspoiled...kill the others.


STRIDER
1 You draw far too much attention to yourself...Mr. Underhill
2 A little more caution from you...that is no trinket you carry.
3 Indeed? I can usually avoid being seen if I wish, but to disappear entirely... that is a rare gift.
4 Are you frightened?
5 Not nearly frightened enough. I know what hunts you. Frodo jumps at the sound of a noise in the corridor.
6 You have a stout heart, little Hobbit, but that alone won't save you...You can no longer wait for the Wizard, Frodo. They're coming.
7 They were once men.
8 Great Kings of men. Then Sauron the deceiver gave to them Nine Rings of Power. Blinded by their greed they took them without question, one by one falling into darkness and now they are slaves to his will.
9 They are the Nazgul, Ringwraiths, neither living or dead. At all times they feel the presence of the ring...drawn to the power of the one..they will never stop hunting you.
10 Into the wild.
11 But where is he leading us?
12 To Rivendell, Master Gamgee...to the house of Elrond.
13 Gentlemen, we do not stop until nightfall.
14 You've already had it.
15 He's been stabbed by a Morgul blade. The Morgul Blade suddenly melts...vanishing into the air like smoke.
16 This is beyond my skill to heal.  He needs Elvish medicine.
17 Hurry!
18 Hold on, Frodo.
19 No. He is passing into the shadow world, he will soon become a wraith like them.
20 Sam, do you know the Athelas plant?
21 Kingsfoil.
22 It may help to slow the poison. Hurry!
23 Dartho guin Berian...rych le ad tolthathon. Stay with the hobbits...I'll send horses for you.
24 Andelu I ven. The road is too dangerous.
25 Arwen...ride hard, don't look back.
26 The same blood flows in my veins...the same weakness...
27 Nauthannim I ned ol reniannen. I thought I had strayed into a dream.
28 You said you'd bind yourself to me, forsaking the immortal life of your people.
29 You cannot give me this.
30 You cannot wield it. None of us can. The one ring answers to Sauron alone...it has no other master.


ARWEN
1 What is this? A Ranger caught off his guard?
2 Frodo, Im Arwen...telin let thaed. I am Arwen, I have come here to help you.  Lasto Beth nin, tolo Dan na ngalad. Hear my voice, come back to the light.
3 Frodo?
4 He's fading...he's not gong to last. We must get him to my father.
5 I have been looking for you for two days.
6 There are five Wraiths behind you, where the other four are, I do not know.
7 Hon mabathon. Rochoh ellint im. I'll take him. I'm the faster rider.
8 Frodo Fir. Ae anthradon I hir, tur gwaith nin beriatha hon. If I can cross the river, the power of my people can protect him.
9 I do not fear them.
10 Noro Lim, Asfaloth, Noro Lim!
11 Noro lim, Asfaloth!
12 If you want him, come and claim him.
13 Non o Chithaeglir, lasto Beth daer: Rimmo nin Briunen Dan in Ulaer! Nin o Chitaeglir, lasto Beth daer: Rimmo nin Bruinen Dan in Ulaer!
14 No, no...Frodo, no! Frodo, don't give in...not now!
15 What grace is given me, let it pass to him. Let him be spared. Save him.
16 Why do you fear the past? You are Isildur's heir...not Isildur himself. You are not bound to his fate.
17 Your time will come. You will face the same evil...and you will defeat it.
18 A si i-duath u-orthor, Aragorn...u or le a u or nin. The shadow does not hold sway yet...not over you and not over me.
19 Renech I lu I erui govannem? Do you remember when we first met?
20 Gwenin in enniath...u-arnech in naeth I se celich. Long years have passed...you did not have the care you carry now.
21 Renech I Beth I pennen? Do you remember what I told you?
22 And to that I hold. I would rather share one lifetime with you than face all the ages of this world alone.
23 I choose a mortal live.
24 It is mine to give to whom I will, like my heart.


BOROMIR
1 The shards of Narsil...the blade that cut the Ring from Sauron's hand.
2 Still sharp.
3 But no more than a broken heirloom.
4 replaces the Broken blade, but it clatters to the floor.
5 So it is true!
6 It is a gift...a gift to the foes of Mordor! Why not use this Ring? Long has my father, the Steward of Gondor, held the forces of Mordor at bay...by the blood of our people are your lands kept safe. Give Gondor the weapon of the enemy...let us use it against him!
7 And what would a ranger know of this matter?
8 Aragorn? This is Isildur's heir?
9 Gondor needs no king.
10 One does not simply walk into Mordor. Its black gates are guarded by more than just Orcs. There is evil there that does not sleep and the Great Eye is ever watchful. It is a barren wasteland, riddled with fire and ash and dust...the very air you breathe is a poisonous fume. Not with ten thousand men could you do this. It is folly.
11 And if we fail, what then? What happens when Sauron takes back what is his?
12 You carry the fate of us all, little one.
13 If this is indeed the will of the Council, then Gondor will see it done.
14 Get away from the blade, Pippin...on your toes...good, very good...I want you to react, not think.
15 Move your feet.
16 It's moving fast...against the wind.
17 Merry..Pippin...Sam...take cover!
18 It is a strange fate that we should suffer so much fear and doubt over so small a thing...such a little thing.
19 As you wish. I care not.
20 We must get off the mountain! Make for the gap of Rohan and take the West road to my city.
21 This is no mine...it's a tomb!
22 We make for the Gap of Rohan. We should never have come here.
23 Legolas!
24 They have a cave troll!
25 What is this new devilry?
26 Give them a moment...for pity's sake!
27 I will find no rest here. I heard her voice inside my head...she spoke of my father and the fall of Gondor, and she said to me: "Even now, there is hope left. But I cannot see it...it is long since we had any hope.
28 My father is a noble man, but his rule is failing and our..our people lose faith. He looks to me to make things right...and I would do it, I would see the glory of Gondor restored. Have you ever seen it, Aragorn? The White Tower of Ecthelion, glimmering like a spike of pearl and silver, its banners caught high in the morning breeze...have you ever been called home by the clear ringing of silver trumpets?
29 One day our paths will lead us there, and the tower guards shall take up the call "the Lords of Gondor have returned."
30 None of us should wander alone; you least of all. So much depends on you...Frodo?
31 I know why you seek solitude. You suffer, I see it day by day. Are you sure you do not suffer needlessly?
32 Let me help you. There are other ways, Frodo..other paths that we might take.
33 Warning? Against what?
34 We are all afraid, Frodo. But to let that fear drive us to destroy what hope we have...don't you see that is madness?
35 I ask only for the strength to defend my people.  If you would but lend me the ring...
36 Why do you recoil? I am no thief.
37 What chance do you think you have? They will find you, they will take the ring and you will beg for death before the end.
38 You fool! It is not yours save by unhappy chance...it might have been mine. It should be mine. Give it to me! Give me the ring.
39 I see your mind...you will take the ring to Sauron. You will betray us! You go to your death and the death of us all. Curse you! Curse you and your Halflings!
40 Frodo! Frodo! What have I done. Please, Frodo...
41 I'm sorry, Frodo...Frodo...
42 Run! Run!
43 They took the little ones...
44 Frodo...where is Frodo?
45 Then you did what I could not. I tried to take the ring from him.
46 Forgive me, I did not see..I have failed you all.
47 Leave it! It is over...the world of Men will fall and all will come to darkness and my city to ruin..Aragorn..
48 Our people...our people...
49 I would have followed you, my brother...my captain, my King.


LEGOLAS
1 Sauron's Ring! The ring of power!
2 This is no mere Ranger. He is Aragorn, son of Arathorn. You owe him your allegiance.
3 And heir to the throne of Gondor.
4 Have you heard nothing Lord Elrond has said? The ring must be destroyed.
5 And you have my bow.
6 Crebain from Dunland!
7 There is a fell voice in the air.
8 Goblins!
9 We must move on, we cannot linger.
10 Orcs !
11 A lament for Gandalf...
12 I have not the heart to tell you. For me, the grief is still too near.
13 We should leave now.
14 It is not the Eastern shore that worries me.
15 A shadow and a threat has been growing in my mind. Something draws near, I can feel it.
16 The horn of Gondor!
17 If we are quick, we will catch Frodo and Sam before nightfall.
18 You mean not to follow them...


GIMLI
1 The doom of man!
2 Then...what are we waiting for?
3 And I suppose you think you're the one to do it?
4 I will be dead before I see the Ring in the hands of an Elf!
5 Never trust an Elf!
6 And my axe.
7 If anyone were to ask for my opinion, which I note they have not, I would say we are taking the long way round. Gandalf, we can pass through the Mines of Moria. My cousin, Balin, would give us a royal welcome.
8 Nothing...it's just a wisp of a cloud.
9 We cannot pass over the mountain. Let us go under it. Let us go through the mines of Moria.
10 The walls of Moria!
11 So, master elf, you will enjoy the fabled hospitality of the dwarves; roaring fires, malt beer, red meat off the bone. This, my friend, is the home of my cousin, Balin...and they call this a Mine...  A mine!
12 Oh...no...no..no... ! Legolas pulls a crude arrow out of a skeleton.
13 No...no...oh, no!
14 Let them come! There is one Dwarf yet in Moria who still draws breath!
15 Mithril! You are full of surprises, Master Baggins.
16 Nobody tosses a dwarf! The BALROG smashes through the wall and spreads its vast wings. It swoops down past the Fellowship, disappearing into a flaming pit!
17 Stay close, young hobbits..they say a Sorceress lives in these woods. An elf- witch of terrible power. All who look upon her fall under her spell...
18 And are never seen again!
19 Well, here's one dwarf she won't ensnare so easily. I have the eyes of a hawk and the ears of a fox!
20 Aragorn! These woods are perilous. We should go back.
21 Oh, yes, just a simple matter of finding our way through Emyn Muil, an impassable labyrinth of razor sharp rocks. And after that gets even better...a festering, stinking marshland, far as the eye can see.
22 Recover my...
23 Then it has all been in vain...the fellowship has failed.
24 Yes! Ha!


ARAGORN
1 Havo dad, Legolas...Sit down, Legolas..
2 If, by my life or death, I can protect you, I will.  ...you have my sword.
3 Hide!
4 Boromir?
5 Boromir...give the ring to Frodo.
6 He's trying to bring down the mountain. Gandalf! We must turn back!
7 The Gap of Rohan takes us too close to Isengard.
8 Mines are no place for a Pony, even one so brave as Bill.
9 Go on, Bill, go on..don't worry, Sam...he knows his way home.
10 Do not disturb the water.
11 Get back! Stay close to Gandalf.
12 Frodo!!
13 You should be dead. That spear would've skewered a wild boar!
14 Gandalf!
15 Legolas, get them up!
16 By nightfall these hills will be swarming with Orcs! We must reach the woods of Lothlorien. Come, Boromir, Legolas, Gimli, get them up. On your feet, Sam. 
17 Frodo? Frodo!
18 Haldir of Lorien, we come here for your help. We need your protection.
19 Take some rest..these borders are well protected.
20 I have seen the white city..long ago.
21 Frodo.
22 The Argonath...
23 Long have I desired to look upon the kings of old...my kin.
24 We cross the lake at nightfall, hide the boats and continue on foot..we approach Mordor from the North.
25 That is our Road...I suggest you take some rest and recover your strength, Master Dwarf.
26 No. Orcs patrol the Eastern shore. We must wait for cover of darkness.
27 Frodo?
28 Where is the ring?
29 Frodo...I swore to protect you.
30 I would have gone with you to the end... into the very fires of Mordor.
31 Go, Frodo!
32 Run! Run!!
33 Boromir!
34 I let Frodo go.
35 The ring is beyond our reach now.
36 No, Boromir. You fought bravely. You have kept your honor.
37 I do not know what strength is in my blood, but I swear to you... I will not let the White City fall, nor your people fail...
38 Be at peace, son of Gondor.
39 They will look for his coming from the white tower...but he will not return.
40 Frodo's fate is no longer in our hands.
41 Not if we hold true to each other. We will not abandon Merry and Pippin to torment and death, not while we have strength left.
42 Leave all that can be spared behind...
43 We travel light. Let's hunt some Orc.
